<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes notes-type="author-contribution">
 <title>Authors' contributions</title>
 <p>J.R.: Shared first authorship. Substantial contributions to the conception and design of the study, analysis and interpretation of data, drafting, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of the whole study are appropriately investigated and resolved. G.R.: Shared first authorship. Substantial contributions to the conception and design of the study, analysis and interpretation of data, drafting, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of the whole study are appropriately investigated and resolved. C.B.: Substantial contributions to the design of the study, analysis and interpretation of data, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. C.G.: Substantial contributions to the design of the study, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. S.D.: Substantial contributions to the design of the study, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. A.B.: Substantial contributions to the design of the study, interpretation of data, revising the work critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p>
</notes>
