<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The interviews yielded information on some key effects of the initiative. First, the Domestic Violence Consultation Plus budget (US$3.5 million in total) is provided for the All Japan Women’s Shelter Network private shelters to undertake domestic violence consultations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Second, Domestic Violence Consultation Plus is free of charge for survivors because of this subsidy (until recently, it was not funded by the government). This service is carried out in approximately 70 private shelters across Japan. There are currently four on-demand Domestic Violence Consultation Plus phonelines in operation. Domestic Violence Consultation Plus handled 1741 cases between 20–30 April 2020, and over 4000 cases every month between May and September 2020.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
 </sup> However, demand for the service is much higher because only about 20% of callers are currently connected. The on-duty system handles calls from across the country, many from survivors in remote areas. If a caller needs protection, their call is transferred to a Domestic Violence Consultation Plus coordinator for information on private shelters in the caller’s area. This entire mechanism was created by a private national shelter network, in collaboration with other support centres. It is not sufficient for a survivor of domestic violence to simply consult and be listened to, because if there is no subsequent safety net, the survivor will not be protected. Third, support for temporary protection at private shelters and business hotels was expanded. For people who receive protection by connecting with Domestic Violence Consultation Plus, accommodation at a shelter or a business hotel is covered by the subsidy. Fourth, there is provision of human resources from private shelters, including, for example, meeting with people who had fled their homes, help in addressing procedures at government offices, accompanying the survivors to medical institutions, etc. Until recently, such inputs had been provided by volunteers who received no payment, but now these volunteers can receive money from the government subsidy.
</p>
